Ladies and gentlemen.
观众朋友大家好
Welcome to DUFE TV station.
欢迎收看东财大电视台
I'm the substitute host, Shan Dan.
我是代班主持人单单
Recently, two debate teams in our university have
近日我校有两支辩论队
advanced to the top four of the provincial competition.
打进省赛四强
Let me bring you
今天由我单单
a live report today.
为各位带来现场报道
Let's come to Team one first.
我们先来看看一队
Come on, Team one.
来 一队
We're too familiar with them.
我们一队都太熟悉不过
So we won't waste time.
就不浪费时间了
Let's come to Team 235.
来看看二三五队
Come on, Team 235.
来 二三五队
We are the champions!
我们是冠军
Objectively speaking,
从客观上来讲
Nan Bei is right.
南北说的是对的
The opponents are strong.
对手都很强
We'll try our best.
只能说我们尽力吧
We're the strongest even we won't try our best.
不尽力我们也是最强的
It's said that
据说一队的
the leader of Team one Liu Yanze
队长刘彦泽
has been already taken.
已经名花有主了
So
所以
keep your hands
谁也不要给我打他
off him.
主意啊
OK. Come on.
好好好 来来来
Tao Hao, are you nervous today?
陶好 今天紧不紧张
Mmm.
嗯
To be honest,
说实话
I must be a little nervous.
肯定是会有点紧张
But I think
但是我觉得我们的队友
my teammates
都已经做好了
are ready for the competition.
万全的准备
Good luck.
那我看好你哦
Come on, Xiaoyu.
来 小鱼
Mmm, we.
我 我们
Come on.
加油
Are you confident of
下一场比赛
winning the next competition?
你们有信心拿下吗
We'll do our best.
尽全力吧
It seems as if our team is going to win.
看来赢了啊
You should have guessed.
猜都猜得到
If we win,
赢了
we will wait for you in the final.
决赛等你
I found some of my previous feelings
我可算是找回点
while facing Liu Yanze.
对刘彦泽的感觉了
How do you feel?
什么感觉
I want to hit him.
想抽他
Hey.
嘿
Your members are sitting well.
你们的队员坐得好端正
Your members
你们的队员
are very active.
倒是很活跃
Well.
那个
I usually take the method of free range.
我平时都是采取放养的
It can arouse
这样能够调动他们
their enthusiasm.
积极性嘛
Are you too strict with your members?
你是不是管太严了
At least, you should have them...
总要让他们自己能够
You weren't strict at that time.
那时候你倒是管得不严
How did it end?
结果嘞
Ladies and gentlemen.
大家好
Welcome to the semifinal
欢迎来到本次
of the competition.
比赛的半决赛现场
I'm Li Yijie
我是今天比赛的主席
the chief judge of the competition today.
李奕洁
Today, the two teams
今天两支会师
in the semifinal
半决赛的队伍
will discuss which one needs more courage,
将共同探讨接受现实
accepting the reality
还是改变现实
or changing the reality.
更需要勇气这个话题
So the point is that
所以我方的观点是
accepting the reality
接受现实比
needs more courage than changing the reality.
改变现实更需要勇气
Thank you.
谢谢
Good argument. Solid and clear.
立论不错 扎实清晰
But the structure is too old.
就是结构太陈旧了
Three-phase isn't popular now.
现在都不流行三段式了
She's quite used to that.
习惯了
So nostalgic.
这么怀旧啊
It's hard to forget.
忘不了
The definition is good.
那个定义不错
I guess you will
应该会趁我们没有
address refutation in the first round
反应过来
without reply.
放在第一轮质询吧
Yes.
嗯
Whose idea is it?
谁想的
It can be said that
算是
the idea occurred to me because of you.
你帮我想的吧
My fellow debaters pointed out in the argument that
对方辩友的立论中指出
sometimes the reality
有时候现实是
is unchangeable.
不可改变的
So changing the reality
因此改变现实
needs the courage to face despair.
就需要面对绝望的勇气
Am I right, the first debater?
对吗 一辩
Yes.
对 没错
Please give an example
请举个例子
that the reality
这种现实是
is unchangeable.
不可改变的
The third debater, please.
三辩
The attack is so vigorous.
玩这么野
She
她呀
is rather brave.
比较猛
For example, the law of gravitation
比如万有引力定律
is unchangeable reality.
就是不可改变的事实
No, I don't think so really.
不对吧
The gravitation
只在经典物理中
exists only in classical physics.
万有引力才存在
Because gravitation
因为万有引力
is Newton's description
是牛顿对
of reality
现实的一种描述
not reality itself.
而非现实本身
What is the reality? The fourth debater, please.
请问四辩 什么是现实
Reality is
现实就是一种
an objective fact
客观存在的事实
or thing.
或者事物
If Newton's description itself
如果牛顿的描述
does exist,
本身是客观存在的
why can't we
为什么不能称之
call it reality?
为现实呢
Personally I think we can.
我想是可以的
If reality cannot be changed,
如果现实不可能被改变
what does changing the reality need?
那改变现实
Imagination
需要的到底是想象力
or courage?
还是勇气呢
The first debater, please.
一辩
Try to do what is impossible.
知其不可为而为之
Don't we need courage?
难道不需要勇气吗
Team NEG broke the rules. No asking.
反方违规 不得反问
Xiaoyu is dragged down to Yin Nan's level.
小鱼跟殷楠不学好啊
She has a memory like a fish.
不长记性
Don't blame her.
你还说人家
I remembered that you always raced to be the first to
我记得当时你
answer questions and asked when you worried at that time.
一着急就抢答反问
So you always broke the rules.
老是犯规
So they are
所以说就是
dragged down to my level.
他们老是不学好
The second debater in your team is good.
你们这个二辩不错啊
She's calm.
很冷静
She
她呀
was not always like that.
她以前可不是这样
She is a habitual criminal
也是个惯犯
like you.
跟你一样
But your refutation in this round
不过你们这一轮质询
has not been substantially advanced.
没有实质性的推进啊
It's good to play for a draw.
打个平手也不错呀
Really?
是吗
But I think
我怎么觉得
you have lost
是丢掉了
a pre-emptive chance.
先发制人的好机会呢
My fellow debaters.
对方辩友你们好
Does accepting the reality
按照您方的意思
means changing ourselves
接受现实就是
according to you?
改变自己对吗
The fourth debater, please.
四辩
Yes.
是的
So what's your standard
那您方判断
to judge which one
谁更需要的
needs more courage?
标准是什么呢
The first debater, please.
一辩
The more difficult it is
哪个更困难
the more courage it needs.
哪个就更需要勇气
Why is it more difficult
为什么改变自己
to change ourselves
要比改变世界
than to change the world?
更加困难呢
Is your standard
难道您方的标准
based on
是建立在唯心
idealism?
主义的基础上吗
The third debater, please.
三辩
Of course not.
当然不是
Your side defined
您方定义
changing the reality as the objective
改变现实是客观
while accepting the reality as the subjective.
而接受现实是主观
It is problematic.
这本身就有问题的
So what is accepting the reality?
那请问什么叫接受现实
It is a state
就是对现实
of not
不做任何
making any changes to reality.
改变的一个状态
Making a decision is certainly
做决定当然是
a psychological process.
一个心理过程
Why is the psychological process
为什么心理过程
not subjective?
不是主观的呢
The first debater, please.
一辩
Yes.
对
Making a decision
做决定是一个
is a subjective psychological process.
主观的心理过程
But changing the reality
可是改变现实
also needs to make a decision.
不也需要做出决定吗
Isn't it also a subjective
这不同样也是一个
psychological process?
主观的心理过程吗
So what we want to compare today is
所以我们今天要比较的
which one needs more courage
就是这两者之间
between the two.
谁更需要勇气
Changing the reality
改变现实是
is a subjective process.
一个主观过程
My fellow debater want to tell me that
对方辩友想告诉我
high buildings rise from the ground
万丈高楼平地起
to hold back Wushan mountains' clouds and rain
截断巫山云雨
till a smooth lake rises in the narrow gorges.
高峡出平湖
All of these depend on
这都是靠主观
subjective imagination?
想象完成的吗
The first debater, please.
一辩
No.
不是
The point of your side is
您方的观点是
the more difficult it is, the more courage it needs.
越困难越需要勇气
So
那么再次请问
why is it more difficult
为什么改变世界
to change the world
要比改变自己的内心
than to change our hearts?
更加困难呢
Change the
到底是改变
law of gravitation
万有引力定律
or challenge the unfairness
还是个人挑战
of the society alone.
整个社会的不公
Which one is
哪一个
easier than psychological construction?
比做心理建设更简单呢
I messed up.
我搞砸了
We're done.
完了
The judgment and definition
这判断跟定义
are both lost.
全都给丢掉了
Team NEG attacked the argument
对方用观众的第一反应
with the audience's first reaction.
来攻击论点
And they forcibly linked
强行将接受
accepting and changing the reality
现实与改变现实
with subjectivity
和主客观
and objectivity.
性质联系在一起
That made our argument
一下子就让我们的论点
sound very ridiculous suddenly.
显得非常地可笑
Do you think there's
你觉得我们的进攻
something wrong with our attack?
有问题
Your analogy itself
你们这层类比本身
is very problematic.
就很有问题
You equated the movements of
你们把改变现实
changing the reality
和改造世界的
with changing the world.
行动等同起来
In fact,
其实呢
we ignored
却忽略了
it must be psychological activities
需要勇气的
that take courage
一定是心理活动
not the action itself.
而非行动本身
Sure.
没错
But now you have an
可是现在场面上
overwhelming advantage on the scene.
你们已经压倒性优势了
How to
这层意思
express the meaning
要怎么有效地
effectively?
表达出来呢
If I were the debater...
如果是我
You will choose to attack.
你会选择进攻
Yes.
没错
Now it's time for the third debater of Team AFF
下面有请正方
to refute.
三辩进行质询
You defined accepting the reality as
您方定义接受现实是
"not rejecting".
不拒绝
But "not rejecting" is
而不拒绝是一个
a passive behavior.
被动行为
So what courage does
请问被动行为
a passive behavior need?
需要什么勇气呢
The third debater, please.
三辩
So it takes more courage
所以改变现实
to change the reality.
更需要勇气啊
You think it takes no courage
那您方认为是接受现实
to accept the reality,
是完全不需要
right?
勇气的是吗
The first debater, please.
一辩
What we discuss today
今天讨论的
is not about whether your side needs courage
不是您方需不需要勇气
but to compare
而是将接受
accepting the reality
现实与改变现实
with changing the reality.
两者进行比较
It certainly takes courage
您方接受现实固然
for your side to accept the reality.
需要勇气
But it is less than
但不如我方改变
our side to change the reality.
现实更需要
When does "not rejecting"
那什么时候
take courage?
不拒绝也需要勇气呢
The fourth debater, please.
四辩
Why did Nan Bei
南北
ask so many questions
为什么对自己的持方
about his motion
给对手问了
of the other side?
这么多问题啊
I don't know.
不知道
He must play his ace in the end.
应该有大招
This is called Socratic method.
这叫苏格拉底辩论法
Constantly develop continuous questions
不断地针对对方的观点
about the point of the other side
发展成延续性的提问
until refutation.
直到出现驳论
Why not ask questions
那为什么
about his own motion?
不问自己的持方呢
But the argument belongs to the other side.
可是论点是对方的呀
I got it.
哦
For example, I don't like
比如我有一个不喜欢的
my blind date.
相亲对象
But due to my face
但是碍于面子
I still have to go to dinner with her.
我还是要跟她去吃饭
I can't reject.
我没有办法拒绝
Is it a kind of courage
这个时候是不是
this time?
一种勇气
Is this courage
这份勇气到底
used in not rejecting
是用在不拒绝上
or in the
还是用在
psychological process
下定决心的这个
of making up your mind?
心理过程中呢
The third debater, please.
三辩
The latter.
后者
The psychological process itself
这个心理过程
is an proactive behavior.
本身就是一个主动行为
But courage
而勇气
only matters on proactive behaviors.
只作用于主动行为上
Your side defined
而您方对于接受现实
accepting the reality as a passive behavior.
定义为是被动行为
Isn't it contrary to
这和我们今天聊的
what we discuss today?
难道不是背道而驰的吗
The fourth debater, please.
四辩
The point is that the psychological process
问题是心理的过程
can guide behaviors
可以指导我们
in the reality.
现实的行为
Isn't it the same?
这不是一件事情吗
If it is the same,
如果是一回事的话
isn't the analysis and distinguishment of
那刚刚您方二辩
subjectivity and objectivity
所做的主客分析和区分
by the second debater
难道不就
of your side meaningless?
没有意义了吗
The psychological process
不论是接受现实
guides practical action
还是改变现实
no matter to accept
都是心理过程
or change the reality.
来指导实际行动吧
Bravo!
漂亮
Better than before.
拉回来一点
Not bad.
还不错
My fellow debaters.
对方辩友你们好
When you make a decision
当你们做一个
facing the unknown
决定的时候
and the known,
面对未知和已知
is it more difficult
是不是未知
when you face the unknown?
更困难一点呢
The fourth debater, please.
四辩
For example, there are two buttons
如果我的面前
in front of me.
有两个按钮
I'll die if I push the first one.
第一个按下去我会死
I don't know what is going to happen
第二个按下去
if I push the second.
我不知道会发生什么
The known is more frightening
在这种情况下
than the unknown in the circumstances.
已知比未知更恐惧
Are there
那请问社会上
more timeservers
随波逐流的人比较多
or people who brave the wind and the waves
还是勇于
in our society?
乘风破浪的人比较多
The second debater, please.
二辩
People who brave the wind and the waves.
随波逐流吧
Are there
那敢于
more people who dare to
改变现实的人比较多
change the reality
还是敢于
or accept the reality?
接受现实的人比较多
The first debater, please.
一辩
It depends.
这就不一定了
Today the development of the society is flourishing.
今天社会发展良好
Most of us
我们绝大部分人
choose to accept the reality.
都会选择接受现实
But 80 years ago
可是八十年前
during the War of Resistance Against Japan,
抗日战争的时候
didn't the whole nation
难道不是全民族
rise in revolt
奋起反抗
and change the reality of being trampled
改变被日本侵略者
by the Japanese invaders?
蹂躏践踏的现实吗
Very good.
很好
So the history
所以那段历史
greatly demonstrated the courage
是不是极大彰显了
of the Chinese nation, didn't it?
中华民族的勇气呢
Why does the war of resistance need courage?
为什么抗战需要勇气呢
Does it take more courage
是不是改变
to change?
更需要勇气呢
It certainly takes courage
敢于对抗侵略者
to dare to fight against the invaders.
当然需要勇气
But the courage to face ourselves
可是敢于直面自己
and the real reality
面对真正的现实
is even more valuable.
这份勇气就更加可贵
This is the reason why
这就是为什么
the theory of quick victory
在面对日寇之时
that is eager to change the reality
急于改变现实的速胜论
and the theory of inevitable defeat
和无法接受
that cannot accept reality
现实的必败论
have fallen through.
都纷纷破产的原因
Only when we recognize the reality
只有当我们认清现实
can we find the real way to win.
才找到真正的胜利之道
From On Protracted War.
论持久战
A draw.
打平了
Our theoretical logic
我们的理论逻辑
has not been repaired yet.
还没修补呢
If we go on like this
这样下去
you will still win.
还是你们赢
But your team
不过你们这支队伍
is really good.
真的很不错
I'm lucky.
我运气好
You look like you're
看你的样子
back to the past.
感觉又像回到了从前呢
In fact, I...
其实我
Concentrate on the competition.
专心看比赛
OK.
哦
We ask for a pause.
申请暂停
Now Team NEG
现在我们反方队伍
has asked for a tactical pause.
申请战术暂停
A minute and a half.
时间为一分半钟
Make good use of it.
好好利用
During this period, the two teams and coaches
其间两支队伍及教练
can come on stage to communicate with the debaters.
可上台与辩手进行交流
The timing starts right away.
计时马上开始
The next step is to keep
接下来就是要保住
our weak advantage.
咱们的微弱优势
But they have started to
但他们反攻的节奏
counterattack at their own pace.
已经起来了
So I ask for a pause
所以我叫暂停
to upset the pace.
来打乱这个节奏
Well done.
打得漂亮
But the opponent
但是对方仍有
has the weak advantage now.
少量的优势
I reckon
我估摸着
their score is two or three points
总分上要比咱们
higher than us.
领先个两三分
But don't worry.
但是不要怕
We can win back.
咱们一定打得回来
Diandian
典典
The coach of Team NEG asked for a pause
对方教练叫暂停
to upset our pace.
是为了打乱我们的节奏
Don't panic.
不要慌
The most important next
下面最重要的
is to repair our argument.
是修补立论
The next step is the summary.
下一个环节是小结
It's your turn, Ma Nan.
马楠你来
OK.
好
After the pause
暂停结束之后
they should send their fourth debater
他们应该会让四辩来
to summarize.
做小结
Their aim is to repair the argument.
目的是修补立论
No matter what perspective they repair from
不论从哪个角度切
you can break it
我们都按照原
according to the original plan.
计划做拆解
Got it?
明白吗
OK. I see.
好 明白 知道了
The summary
小结
should avoid the attack point just now.
绕开刚才的进攻点
Break their point from
从改变现实不具
changing the reality
有绝对可行性
does not have absolute feasibility.
来拆解对方立场
What do you think about it?
怎么样
You're right.
对
Because there are many infeasibility in reality.
因为现实有很多不可行
It is meaningless to simply equate it
单纯的等同于困难程度
with the degree of difficulty.
就没有意义了
Although it doesn't hurt
这虽然不伤害
our argument
我们的立论
the chance of winning is weak.
但胜算太小
No.
不行
I think
我觉得
we should face
我们得直面
the questions in the refutation.
质询中的问题
From
从
the perspective of changing the reality needs more courage.
改变现实更需要勇气走
But the point didn't have a leg
可是这个点刚才
to stand on just now.
已经被打掉了
We can win back.
可以打回来
We can win only in this way.
只有打回来才能赢
Are you quite sure?
有把握吗
The coaches of the two teams have to go back now.
请两队教练回到观众席
The competition will go on.
比赛继续
Believe me.
相信我
I believe you.
嗯 我相信你
Come on.
加油
Don't worry, Sa.
放心吧 小撒
It's taken by surprise.
措手不及
OK. The competition goes on.
好 那么比赛环节继续
Now let's invite one debater from Team AFF
下面有请正方任意辩手
to make a summary of refutation.
做质询小结
Thank you, the chief judge.
谢谢主席
Ladies and gentlemen.
大家好
There must be one team
今天这场比赛
losing in the
我们当中必然有一方
competition today.
将止步于此 含恨离场
But when we have to
但当我们需要面对
face the difficulties,
困难的时候
how should we choose?
应该如何选择
Face it
面对它
or escape from it?
还是逃避它
It's really easy to escape from the reality.
逃避现实真的很容易
I can make a scene.
我可以大闹会场
I can say
我可以说
there is an inside story of a plot.
这场比赛有黑幕
I can no longer participate
我可以从此不再
in the debate.
参加辩论
I can also say I'm not the loser.
我也可以说我没有失败
But what if I face it?
但是如果面对它呢
I must admit that
我必须承认自己
I am inferior to others in skills.
技不如人
I should thank the opponent.
我要感谢对方
Even if I have reluctance and regret,
即使自己有不甘和遗憾
I should face it with a smile.
也要微笑着去面对
But for every debater
但是对于每个辩手而说
are you convinced of the result
每场比赛都
of each game?
输得心服口服吗
For adjudicators of the debate competition
对于辩论赛的评判来说
is there an absolute
有一个绝对
objective standard?
客观的标准吗
No.
没有
But when we lose
但当我们每次输掉
in a competition we don't think
我们认为不该输的
we will lose,
比赛时
when we can't take part in
当我们不能再代表
the competition on behalf of the school,
自己学校参赛时
or when we have to
当我们为了自己的热爱
take part in some competitions
必须去参加一些
those can hardly be termed competitions,
不算比赛的比赛时
how should we choose?
我们应该如何选择
Face it or escape from it?
面对它 还是逃避它
My fellow debaters said
对方辩友说
changing the reality means
改变现实是
fighting against the rules of the world.
对抗这个世界的规则
It's very difficult.
这很难
Changing the reality
改变现实面对的
will face everything unknown.
是一切未知
It's very difficult.
这很难
Changing the reality
改变现实还有一种
will face a huge risk.
巨大的风险叫
I will lose more.
我可能失去更多
It's very difficult.
这很难
But my fellow debaters.
但对方辩友
There is one thing
有一样东西改变起来
more difficult
比这些所有加起来
and arduous
都要难
than the sum total of the all.
都要艰巨得多
Ourselves.
那就是我们自己
When we should accept the reality,
当我们接受的是现实
it means we should change ourselves.
那意味着要改变自己
When we should accept
当我们坦然接受
the fact that we should have a fight
要战斗的事实
it means we should
那意味着要
change our weakness.
改变懦弱的自己
When we should accept
当我们要接受
the reality of losing our relatives,
失去亲人的现实
it means we should change
那意味着要改变
ourselves who are used to rely on others.
这个习惯于依赖的自己
When we should accept ourselves
如果要接受
who have missed their true love
曾经因为他的懦弱
because of
和犹豫
our weakness and hesitation
失去了一生的真爱
or who have done a lot of stupid things
因为之前的迷茫和胆小
and said a lot of stupid words
做了很多糊涂事
because of our confusion
也说了很多
and shyness,
糊涂话的自己的时候
we must
我们必须
change ourselves
把自己改变成敢于追求
to people who dare to pursue and know what we want.
并且知道自己想要什么
Isn't it difficult?
这不困难吗
It's too difficult.
这太困难了
We think
我方认为
accepting the reality
接受事实
takes more courage than changing the reality.
比改变事实更需要勇气
Because it's a
因为这是一个
natural process.
坦然的过程
It's a process
这是一个自我
of cultivating ourselves.
塑造的过程
In this process
在这个过程里
although we're in a swamp,
我们虽身处泥沼
our hearts are pursuing the starlight.
但心向星光
Thank you.
谢谢
Now I have
现在比赛结果
got the result.
已经在我手上
The winner of this competition is
本次比赛的获胜方是
Team 235.
二三五辩队
Congratulations! Team 235 has advanced to the finals.
恭喜二三五冲入决赛
I didn't launch a fierce attack
我要不看在小撒的
for the sake
面子上
of Sa.
我早就大杀四方了
Let him treat.
让他请客
I don't think he has time
我估计他这会儿
at the moment.
没啥心思
Congratulations!
恭喜
Thank you.
谢谢
Hold her hands. Stupid.
拉手啊 傻瓜
Hold her hands.
拉人手啊
Stay here.
留下 留下来
I'm sorry to trouble you today.
今天麻烦你了
Thank you for giving me a ride specially.
还让你专门送我一趟
Throw the suitcase into the fountain.
把行李箱扔到喷泉里啊
Is it heavy?
沉吧
No.
不沉
No, no, no.
不沉 不沉 不沉
Come on. Don't let her go.
上啊 不能让她走啊
Come on. Keep her.
上啊 留住她呀
Kabe-Don! Kiss her!
壁咚啊 强吻啊
Sorry, sorry.
不好意思 不好意思
I'm too excited.
我太激动了
Well.
那
Bye.
再见
Wait, wait, wait.
哎哎哎
She left.
走了
Wait.
哎
Diandian
典典
So quick.
停这么快
I thought I was going to chase for a while.
我还以为要追一会儿
-What's wrong with you?  -Diandian.
怎么样 典典
Are you OK?
没事吧
Diandian, please don't go.
典典 不要走
Don't go to Canada.
不要去什么加拿大
Can you stay here?
留下来好吗
No. I'll go with you
不 就算要走的话
if you have to go.
我跟你一起
Will you take me with you?
带上我好不好
I don't want to lose you again.
我不想再放过你了
I don't want to
我不想
see you again
等到我们老了的时候
only when we get old.
我才能见到你
I don't want to
我更不想从现在开始的
regret your leave
每一分每一秒
and my weakness
我都去后悔
from now on.
当初我为什么要让你走
I don't want anything.
我什么都不要了
You take me away
要么
like your
你像一件行李一样
luggage
把我带走
or stay here for me.
要么 留下来
I must go to Canada.
我必须要去加拿大
But
但是
I go there for visiting my relatives.
我是去探亲
I'll be back.
还会回来的
You can't
我这次回来
leave me alone this time.
你可不许再跑了
The final of the provincial debate league
本届省辩论联赛的决赛
will be held in two days.
将在两日后举行
The two teams in the final
挺进决赛的两支队伍
are School Debate Team of DUFE
分别是我校校辩论队
and the original Team two of DUFE
和我校原二队
Team 235 now.
现在的二三五辩论队
The school team
我校校队
led by Liu Yanze
在队长刘彦泽的带领下
advanced to the final first
以总积分第一的成绩
as the top in total points.
最先闯入决赛
It is worth recalling that
值得一提的是
the team
四名选手在去年联赛中
had once been the runner-up
以同样的配置
with the same lineup in the league last year.
获得了亚军的优异成绩
As the last social team
而二三五队
to have the chance
作为最后一支
to advance to the league,
获得联赛名额的社会队
Team 235 was not favored at the beginning.
最初并不被看好
But as the dark horse
但作为本次赛事中
of the competition,
最大的黑马
it advanced to the final
最终以全胜纪录
with the record of a complete victory.
杀入决赛
Please look forward to
让我们敬请期待
the summit competition.
这场巅峰对决
Captain Tao Hao
陶好队长
That was a surprise hit
这次比赛你们爆
that you had won in the semifinal.
了个大冷门
Did you think about it before the competition?
赛前有想到吗
We didn't think too much
我们一开始也
at the beginning.
没有想那么多
We just want to
只想着把每
try our best in every competition.
一场比赛都打好
Well. We don't have to think about it at all.
那个 根本就不用想
The result
都是我们
met my expectations.
意料之中的事情
The opponent in the final is still Team one.
决赛的对手还是一队
They defeated you
之前有过
twice before.
两次败北的纪录
Do you have confidence this time?
这次有信心吗
We will continue to work hard.
我们会继续努力的
Of course we have confidence.
我们当然有信心了
Especially confident.
特别有信心
I can tell you.
我跟你说
We had
一队在学校里
put ourselves through the mill
趴窝的时候
for a long time
我们在外边早磨炼
when Team one stayed in its comfort zone at school.
很多久了
Ma Nan
马楠同学
As Hisashi Mitsui of Team 235,
作为二三五队的三井寿
how do you feel to return
再次回归赛场
to the competition?
有什么感触呢
I think Tao Hao
我觉得陶好之前
was hard because
带这些问题儿童
she led the problem children before.
还是挺辛苦的
Let me introduce
我给大家介绍一下
myself to all of you.
我自己啊
I'm the mainstay
我是我们二三五队的
of Team 235.
中流砥柱
I'm Nan Bei.
我叫南北
I have the appearance of Kaede Rukawa
是那个流川枫的外貌
and
然后那个那个那个
and the ability of...
那谁的 实力
No, no. The ability.
别别 实力
I, I'm
我 我就是
Nan Bei. Thank you.
南北 谢谢大家
Please remember me. Thank you.
请大家记住我 谢谢
So what do you think
那你们认为这次比赛
is the key to win?
胜负的关键在哪儿
Maybe Liu Yanze of Team one.
可能是一队的刘彦泽吧
No, it's me.
不是 我 是我
How do you feel?
怎么样
Have you been intoxicated
有没有陶醉在
with my beauty?
我的盛世美颜里
If I
你说
break up with you
我要是因为你
because you
太丢辩论队的人
have humiliated our team enough,
跟你分手了
I am not unreasonable, am I?
不算是无理取闹吧
Ah!
哎呀
I found that you have
我发现这几天
lost your fighting will
你们呐
these days.
都没有了之前的斗志
Even Dango
就连团子这种
whose mind is empty
脑子不装事的人
starts getting depressed.
都开始抑郁了
Why is my mind empty?
我怎么就脑子不装事了
I'm just nervous.
我那是紧张
I'm nervous, too.
我也挺紧张的
I have not
我都已经两天
slept well for two days.
没有怎么睡好觉了
Aren't you nervous, Nan Bei?
你不紧张 南北
I only have
我只有大仇
the excitement of revenge.
将报的兴奋感
How about you, Ma Nan?
马楠 你呢
I don't have a strong feeling.
我没什么感觉
But if Hao is nervous,
但是如果小好紧张的话
I can cultivate myself in advance.
我可以提前培养一下
Thank you.
谢谢
I wonder
我就纳闷了
why you're so nervous.
你们都紧张个什么劲啊
We are only one step away
咱们离冠军
from the champions.
只有一步之遥了
How to say?
怎么说呢
When You have a goal
就是你有一个目标
that is still far away,
当它还很远的时候
you rush forward like
你就像打了鸡血一样
you are full of beans.
特别有劲地往前冲
But when the goal
但这个目标
is easily available,
突然触手可及了
you start worrying about personal gains and losses,
你就患得患失了
You're afraid of a moment of inattention
生怕一个不小心
ah?
哎
then your efforts will be in vain,
之前的努力就都白费了
Yes.
对
Although I can't sum it up
我虽然总结不出来
I feel like this.
但就是这种感觉
Why can't I feel it?
我怎么就是感觉不到呢
Sorry.
对不起
I thought you had were careless.
还以为你谁呢
You are insensitive actually.
太大条了吧
It is good.
也是好事
All right.
好了好了
We're going to take part in the competition soon.
马上就要参加比赛了
It's normal to feel pressure.
有压力是很正常的
We should turn pressure into motive force.
我们要把压力化成动力
Let's get ready for the game.
开始准备比赛吧
Ladies and gentlemen.
各位听众朋友们大家好
Welcome to Campus Radio Broadcasting.
欢迎收听校园广播
I'm the school hunk, Shan Dan.
我是你们的校草单单
As we all know
众所周知
the strongest Team 235 of our school
我校实力最强的
has advanced to
二三五队
the provincial finals
不费吹灰之力
as easy as blowing off dust.
打进了省赛决赛
Although the opponent this time
虽然这一次的对手呢
is Team one
是曾经
which defeated Team 235.
惜败的对手校一队
But over the past year
不过这一年以来
the Team 235 led by Nan Bei
以南北为首的二三五队
remained true to their original aspiration
不忘初心 牢记使命
and kept their mission firmly in mind.
奋发图强 砥砺前进
I'm sure they can
一定能打出
make a wonderful turnaround.
一个漂亮的翻身仗
Here
在这里呢
Nan Bei
南北同学
leaves a message to Liu Yanze.
给刘彦泽同学的留言是
It's
是时候展现
show time.
我们真正的技术了
Mu Xiaoyu leaves
而牧小鱼同学
a message to Yin Nan.
给殷楠同学的留言是
We'll increasingly kick back to you.
我们定将以十倍奉还
All right.
好了
Finally, let's give a song
最后让我们以一首歌曲
to Team 235.
送给二三五队
We are the champion.
我们是冠军
Captain
队长
It is a little too much, isn't it?
这是不是有点过了
You should keep your girlfriend under control.
你女朋友你也不管管
Prepare for the competition.
好好备战
Don't be disturbed by these things.
别被这些事干扰
How much did you pay him?
你给了多少钱
That's all from my heart.
肺腑之言
Nan Bei, how can you defeat
南北 你这样怎么
Liu Yanze like this?
打败刘彦泽呀
Leave him alone.
别管他 别管他
There is something wrong with his brain.
他脑子有问题
Go on, go on.
我们继续 我们继续
Doctor, will you mind repeating that, please?
医生 您 您再说一遍
What diseases?
什么病
Doctor.
医生
Zhang has been in hospital
我们家老张住院
for so long.
都这么长时间了
His condition hasn't improved.
病情也没见好转
You can just tell me
要是有什么你
if there is something serious.
就直接跟我说吧
I can bear it.
我能承受得住
Professor Zhang's disease
教授得的是
is lumbar spinal stenosis.
腰椎锥体狭窄
This is also the reason why
这也是导致他
he often has lumbar and leg pain.
经常腰腿疼痛的原因
In addition, the centrum has a trend
加上有锥体
of hyperosteogeny.
骨质增生的发展趋势
So
所以
I suggest to have an operation
我建议
of laminectomy
尽快做椎板切除
and nerve root decompression as soon as possible.
和神经根减压的手术
Operations?
手术啊
Can he do physical therapy?
那 能不能物理治疗呢
Professor Zhang's left arm
教授的左手臂
and right leg have been numb
和右腿发麻
for half a year, right?
有半年了吧
It seems that way.
是 好
Yes. Half a year, right?
是 半年 对吧
Almost.
差不多
Without the operation
如果不做手术
Professor Zhang's morbidity
教授发病的频率
and intermittent claudication
和间歇性跛行的情况
will become more and more serious.
会越来越严重
Even to the point where
甚至于会发展到
he can't get of bed.
下不了床的情况
What?
啊
Is it so serious?
这么严重吗
What about operative risks?
那 那手术风险
Generally, such an operation
一般这样的手术
has a 90% chance of success.
有九成的把握
Don't worry too much.
也不要太担心
But.
但是
But what?
但是什么
Any operation involves an element of risk.
手术都是有风险的
And your lover
尤其是你爱人的
is old.
年龄偏大
The risk is also increased.
风险也加大
Operation and postoperative recovery
手术跟手术后的恢复
have also changed.
也有所变故
In general, there is a 20% chance
总的来说有两成的几率
that it will affect the results.
会影响结果
There will be paralysis led by
要么是术后恢复不当
improper postoperative recovery
导致瘫痪
or the process of the operation.
要么是手术过程当中
Of course
当然
conservative treatment is also a method.
保守治疗也是一种方法
Make up your mind as soon as possible.
你们尽快拿主意吧
Have a good rest, Professor Zhang.
教授 好好休息
Thank you.
谢谢
Thank you, doctor.
谢谢你啊 医生
There is still a 80% chance of success.
不是还有八成把握吗
It's more than the chance
比明天能醒过来的
of waking up tomorrow.
几率要大
297, 298,
二百九十七 二百九十八
299, 300.
二百九十九 三百
OK, OK.
好 好
Great, great, great.
厉害 厉害 厉害
Tired?
累了吧
Can it really relieve the tension?
这个真的能缓解紧张吗
Sure.
真的
You must get
今天晚上你肯定
a good night's sleep.
能睡个好觉
Why?
为什么
Because you're tired.
因为累了
Can you be serious
你这个时候可不可以
at this time?
正经一点
Look.
你看啊
As a captain
你作为队长
you should be confident
你要对你的队员
in your team.
自信一点
As my girlfriend
那你身为女朋友呢
you should be confident in
就要对你的最佳辩手
your boyfriend
男朋友
who is the best debater.
自信一点
Got it?
知道吧
Yes.
嗯
Then I'll go back to the dormitory.
那我先回宿舍了
Then I'll go back after counting to ten.
那我数十下我就回去
OK.
好
I'm going to count with you.
那我跟你一块数
One.
一
Two.
二
Three.
三
Four.
四
Five.
五
Six.
六
363 mutton shashliks.
三百六十三个羊肉串
364 mutton shashliks.
三百六十四个羊肉串
365 mutton shashliks.
三百六十五个羊肉串
366 mutton shashliks.
三百六十六个羊肉串
367 mutton shashliks.
三百六十七个羊肉串
The winner of this competition is
本场比赛的获胜方为
Team NEG. Congratulations!
反方 恭喜他们
DUFE.
东州财经大学代表队
Not so bad.
还好
My mentality is stable.
心态稳得一批
I'm afraid of a moment of inattention,
总觉得一有闪失
then our efforts
之前所有的努力
will be in vain.
都白费了
Let's talk about
那我们现在来谈一下
debaters of the next competition.
下次比赛上场的人数吧
Of course you four.
当然是我们最强配备
You're the strongest.
你们四个了
Dango
团子
Although you took part in the competition not very often
虽然马楠进队之后
after Ma Nan joined us,
你上场的次数少了
we
但是
never questioned
我们从来没有质疑过
your ability.
你的能力啊
Yes.
对啊
You are also the main force of the school team.
你也是校队主力嘛
If you want to take part in the competition, tell us.
如果你想上场跟我们说
It's OK that you put it forward.
你提出来没关系的
I think Dango...
我觉得团子
Stop.
打住
I know you're going to
知道你又要对
begin a series of personal attacks.
我人身攻击了
I think Dango can take part in the next competition.
我觉得团子可以一战
Who will exit?
那谁下场
Me.
我
You don't want
你不会是想要让我们
us to beg you,
上演一出
do you?
苦苦哀求你的戏码吧
Of course not.
当然没有了
We can consider this problem
我们可以从两个方面
from two aspects.
考虑这个问题
One.
第一呢
The old coach isn't here.
老教练不在
Sa is also
小撒也沉浸在恋爱
immersed in love.
中无法自拔
I can give you some help
我呢 还可以在场外
off the court.
给大家一些援助
Two.
第二呢
I've really been feeling
我最近确实身体
a little sick lately.
有点不舒服
What's wrong with you?
你哪儿不适啊
I've been vomiting lately.
我最近总是吐
And I feel giddy and light-headed.
然后头晕目眩的
I also have ascites.
腹部还有积水
I feel like I've
我感觉我最近人
lost weight recently.
都消瘦了
But my belly is very big.
但是肚子特大
Are you OK?
你没事吧
Can you hold on?
能不能撑住
I don't know.
我不知道
But I feel terrible anyway.
我反正就特别难受
Let's go to the hospital.
要不咱去医院吧
No.
不用啊
I've been there already.
我去过了
The doctor said
医生说
I had to have injections during this period.
我得打一段时间的针
This period?
一段时间啊
It sounds serious.
看来很严重了
Do you have an
你那个针
injection of 411?
是不是叫四一一啊
Yes, yes, yes.
对对对
That's it.
对 就是它
I don't know why I feel terrible.
不知道为什么好难受
You have got feline infectious peritonitis(FIP).
你得的这个是猫传腹
This disease is not contagious.
不传染人的
Still you're such a tease.
什么时候了还开玩笑
Wanna die?
你找死啊你
Ah!
哎呀我
I had a headache.
头疼 头疼
I can't make it.
不行了
I have backache and appendiceal pain.
腰疼 阑尾疼
And I have a stomachache. It hurts everywhere.
肚子疼 哪都疼
Ah!
哎哟
Parents, please pay attention.
广大家长请注意了
FIP is no longer a terminal disease.
猫传腹已不再是绝症
If the babies have continuous low fever,
如出现持续低烧
suffer from loss of appetite
食欲不振
and their globulin ratio
白球比低于
is lower than 0.6,
零点六的宝宝们
please be treated in time.
请及时治疗
They can be saved.
还是可以救活的哟
Does Nan Bei feel sick
南北是不是真的
for real?
不舒服啊
Would you like to visit him?
你要不要去看看
It must be that Xiaoyu
他呀 肯定是最近
has put all her mind
小鱼的心思
on the competition and ignored him.
都在比赛上忽略了他
So he wants to find a sense of existence.
所以就矫情找存在感呗
I guess he was reprimanded too much
估计是昨天被
by us yesterday
咱们给怼狠了
So he wants to pay attention to
今天想要重视一下
this competition today.
这个比赛
Wow!
哇
Hao, did you make a fortune?
小好姐 你发财了
We didn't order so much.
我们没有点这么多呀
For free.
送给你们的
What's wrong?
怎么
Are you familiar
这么久了
with us after so long?
终于混脸熟了
Why did it end so early today?
今天怎么收这么早呀
I want to see Xiaoyang sing.
我还想看小羊唱歌呢
That's it.
就是
Xiaoyang, where are you going?
小羊 你们去哪儿
We are about to graduate.
我们快要毕业了
And the owner here said
而且这儿的老板
it would be renovated.
说要装修
We're leaving.
我们就先撤了
Then tell me
那你们转战去哪儿
your next place.
跟我们说一声
We will visit you
回头我们比赛完了
after the competition.
去看你们
We're disbanded.
我们解散了
What?
解
You're disbanded?
解散了
The band has been established for nearly four years.
乐队成立快四年了
We haven't got something done.
也没做出什么成绩
Shui has been working hard for a long time.
就是辛苦了水哥
We feel sorry for him.
怪对不起他的
It's good.
挺好的
In this way, things will be easier for me.
这样我也轻松多了
I won't wash dishes
以后不用刷碗洗盘子
and be a delivery guy in the future.
跑腿送快递了
Shui has been working to support
一直以来都是水哥打工
the band's expenses.
支撑着乐队的开销
Otherwise, it won't last four years.
不然也不可能撑四年
So
所以啊
for us
这对我们来说
it's a relief.
也算是一种解脱了
We don't know where
就是这些东西
to put these things.
也不知道往哪儿放
How about the loft where we usually train.
要不放我们训练的阁楼
We often train for the debate
反正平时我们都训练
and hardly go there.
平时也不去
That's great.
太好了
Come on.
来
Your gifts.
送你们的
Drink for free.
酒水免单
What about me?
那我也
That's great.
太好了
Shui, I...
水哥 我
OK, you're all in my heart.
行了 都在我的心里面
No.
不是
I mean
我是说能不能
would you mind giving me another one?
再给我一张
I'll give it to my boyfriend.
我给我男朋友
Doctor.
医生
You said there was a 80% chance of success.
您说有八成的希望
That's to say
也就是说
he will be fine, right?
不会有事吧
No operation can guarantee
任何手术
a 100% chance of success.
都不能保证没事
I can only say that the success rate is very high.
只能说成功率很高
Is there any other way
那除了手术
except the operation?
还有其他的办法吗
If you choose conservative treatment
如果保守治疗的话
you can rely on medicine and daily physiotherapy
还像以前一样
just like before.
靠药物和日常理疗
But according to the physical checkup report
但是根据检查报告来看
he has missed
已经错过了
the best period of medicine physiotherapy.
最佳的药物理疗时段
It may cause paralysis.
有可能会引起瘫痪
Of course, it varies from person to person.
当然这个也因人而异
Well, doctor.
那医生
We need to have a discussion.
我们回去商量商量
OK. Make up your mind as soon as possible.
行 需要尽快决定
OK.
哎
Thank you.
那医生谢谢你
You're welcome.
好
Hey!
哎哎哎
What are you eating behind my back?
背着我偷吃什么呢
Let me have a look. Let me have a look.
我看看 我看看
Sa
小撒
He won't do as he is told.
不听话这孩子
I said I couldn't eat greasy food.
我说我不能吃油腻的
I'm sick.
我生病了
The meat is an expression
孩子一番心意
of the good will.
非送这么一个肉来
It's a pity to throw it away. So I...
扔了可惜 我就
OK, OK, OK.
行了 行了 行了
Just one bite.
就吃了一口
Zhang
老伴啊
I have a piece of good news to tell you.
我告诉你一个好消息啊
What?
嗯
I talked with the doctor just now.
刚才我跟医生谈过了
The doctor said
医生说呢
you don't have to
以你目前的情况
have an operation in your current situation.
不用做手术
So
所以呢
you can eat what you want.
你想吃什么就吃什么
Tell me if you want to eat something.
想吃什么呢 就跟我说
I'll cook for you.
我给你去做
But your levels of blood lipids
但是呢 你这个血脂啊
and blood sugar are a little higher.
血糖有点高
So
所以呢
you should control them.
你还得控制一下
Got it?
听明白了吗
You can
老伴
tell me the truth.
说实话吧
How many days can I live?
我还能活几天啊
Bah!
呸
What are you talking about?
瞎说什么呢
I will leave if you say like this.
你再这样我就走了我就
I'm wrong.
我说错了
I just feel that
我就觉得
don't I have to have an operation?
我真的不用做手术了吗
Of course you don't have to have an operation.
当然了 不用做手术了
OK.
好
Happiness comes a little suddenly.
幸福来得有点突然
I'm not used to it.
不太习惯
What do you want to eat for dinner?
你晚上想吃什么
I want to eat kung-pao chicken.
我想吃宫保鸡丁
Kung-pao chicken, right?
宫保鸡丁 是不是
OK, I'll cook for you.
好 我晚上就给你做
It's so kind of you.
老伴真好
Well.
那个
Our two teams
我们两队马上就要
are going to have a competition soon.
比赛了
Is it good that we
总是这样见面
always meet like this?
会不会不是很好啊
How about
要不
not meeting before the game?
比赛前我们先不见
I feel that
我是觉得
perhaps we should avert suspicion before the competition.
可能应该要避避嫌
We don't have to.
不用吧
Really?
真的
It's OK as long as
我们不聊这个
we don't talk about this.
不就好了呗
And
再说
we haven't talked about
我们之前也没聊过
the debate before.
关于辩论的事情
You're right.
也对
I thought you would agree.
我还以为你会同意呢
I know the answer
这种送命题
to the question with potential danger.
我还是知道答案的
By the way.
对了
Nan Bei is odd recently, right?
南北最近是不是很奇怪
How did you know that?
你怎么知道
I saw him in the supermarket just now.
我刚在超市看到他了
What was he doing?
他干嘛
He looked furtive.
挺猥琐的
Nan Bei didn't come to the training again.
南北那货训练又没来
If I grab him later,
我一会儿逮着他
I will fold him and throw him into the city moat
就把他对折扔护城河
to feed the ducks.
里面喂鸭子
It's cruel and useless.
你这招不仅狂野还没用
He won't tell you in this way.
他反而更不会说了
What should I do?
我干嘛 我把他
Bind him down and keep watch on him?
我绑身边我监视他
Don't be too violent.
你俩能不能别那么刺激
At this time
这个时候
you should use
就应该拿出
the weapon of girls.
女孩子的武器
What?
什么武器
Swords, guns or what?
刀 枪 还是什么
I don't mean that.
不是那个武器
It's tenderness.
是温柔
Tenderness?
温
I don't have it.
我不会啊我
Nan Bei, follow me.
南北 你跟我来一下